[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right let's begin welcome to the
stoa
everyone i'm peter limberg the steward
of the stoa
and the stowe is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most
at the nice edge of this very moment and
today we're very lucky because we have
john arquilla
uh and david ronfeld who are both ran
analysts
at ran an author of numerous articles
including
a recently released monograph called
whose story wins the rise of the noah's
fare
uh noah politik and information age
statecraft
and that was just released i think a
month or so ago and
in 1999 they wrote their this was a
follow-up for the
another monograph they wrote called the
emergence of
noah politik uh towards an american
information strategy
and i geek out about this stuff as
everyone knows
and this this one right here actually
influenced um
a white paper i wrote about two years
ago on the medic tribes and then i was
happy to see
that piece was referenced in their new
monograph
uh so that was pretty cool uh and then
uh i invited uh
uh david's a friend on facebook so i
invited them out
i got connected with john so here we are
uh
and what we're gonna do we're gonna kind
of talk about this
monograph um we're gonna kind of
maybe have a conversation for about 15
20 minutes between john and i
if you have any questions throughout you
know the drill if you've been here
before
throw them in the chat i'll call on you
and mute yourself if you don't want to
be on youtube
indicate you want me to read your
question
on your behalf so i think
that is everything i will allow john to
unmute himself
uh hello john again hi peter hi
everybody
um so i was thinking
uh yeah maybe the first question is what
motivated you
and david to write the original uh
monograph you wrote in in 1999 and have
this follow-up and then maybe we could
come to terms with all the different
terms that are there like noah's fear
and no apolitique that people might not
be familiar with
sure well david and i have been trying
to interpret the strategic implications
of the information age for the last 30
years
and just with regard to your
introduction
while i've remained involved with rand
i've actually been at the
united states naval post graduate school
for the last 27 years
but my continued involvement with rand
and with david has been one of the great
privileges
in fact i like to say my best years at
rand were since i left
so we've been thinking about this for
quite a while we developed a concept of
cyber war which
people probably have heard a fair amount
about uh now
and we paid a great deal of attention to
the rise of uh networks
and uh the way they would uh operate we
came up with notions of
uh swarms and
not just swarms of missiles and things
like that but also
social swarms the think of the color
revolutions
the arab spring the sorts of things that
give power to social movements are
really all about
networking and and so uh
as a kind of culminating a piece of that
that first arc of our research
we decided that uh military and defense
affairs
aside it was important to rethink
statecraft more generally
and so it occurred to us that a century
ago
long before the world wide web or the
internet existed
tehar deshardan talked about this globe
girdling realm of the mind that
was one day going to come into being
where all would connect with all and how
it would change
really the way the world operated and
this made a great deal of sense to us we
began to
find bits of evidence of movement in
this direction
but what we realized at the time is that
where
traditional notions of force and
statecraft power in general
have a doctrine associated with them the
notion of rail politique
this is power politics economic pressure
military threats deterrence coercion
all those sorts of things there's a very
well articulated doctrine
for hard power little of that doctrine
works very well i hasten to say
but there isn't really a way of thinking
or acting
or really a set of concepts
for the use of softer ideational power
and so that's really what neopolitique
is all about how would one
take this notion of this globe
globe-girdling realm of the mind
and turn it into something that could uh
actually inform and guide policy
uh leave room for prosperity and peace
and make a world less permissive of the
kinds of conflicts we've seen not only
the last few decades but
really in the 75 years since the end of
world war ii on average the world has
had over 30 wars ongoing at any given
time
there are about 40 going on today
and while we don't have things like
world war ii in terms of many tens of
millions of lives lost
there are countries in which terrible
conflicts are underway in which the
percentage of the populations
is far far greater than suffered in
world war ii when you think about
the five million who died in the congo
the million in syria and of course half
of the country's population made refugee
the charnel house of yemen that exists
today
on on and on and so we think there's
plenty of room
especially because of the very failed
record of traditional rail politique
that there is room for this new approach
i'll i'll pause there to let you
ruminate and ask another question
so uh when i first heard the term noise
here i
i loved it speaking out about i was
using it every time every moment i could
um and so that's maybe what gravitated
to
me to reach out to your original uh book
that you released in 1999
so i'm curious why did you choose that
term
particularly out of all the other terms
out there collective consciousness
and maybe you can speak on the
evolutionary um
aspect of it like the um the geosphere
to the biosphere to the new sphere
sure well nuos of course has the greek
roots of uh the mind
right and so a realm of the mind would
be a noise sphere and we didn't
invent that that term tehar the chardan
was the one who really began it and he's
the one
who saw the evolution of the planet in
terms of
the geosphere it began as the hot rock
uh life came to it whether from you know
the comets dropping water on the planet
or natural condensation cooling
processes
but geosphere went to biosphere
and now at this evolutionary stage we
have the possibility
of this realm of of the mind this newer
sphere
and uh again what what we noticed was
this lack of
any notion of um how one would operate
in terms of state craft and diplomacy
in in the world where there was a new
sphere and i hastened to add that
we aren't the first people to think or
nor was taylor
of this idea of the globe girdling
consciousness
certainly emerson's oversoul
is an idea very consistent with this
and he's not the the only thinker but i
think we have
uh really taken original path here
by suggesting that this concept actually
implies a new way of interacting
with other nations and especially with
the rise of networks this is
i think truly the age of networks this
is the information revolution
is most conducive to the formation of
flat organizational structures of people
drawn together
by a common goal without necessarily any
kind of central control
and as i look at evolution and i think
david does too
we see in the human experience at least
as we
know of it historically empires were the
basic
units that drove human affairs
for millennia until probably around 1500
and in the last 500 years
the nation state began to emerge and
that dominated it basically has crushed
the empires after
uh 500 years of of competition
now is the empire's if you want to
consider the soviet union the last of
the empires or if you'd like to consider
the united states as the last
empire as the empires have
faded away and the nation-states seem
dominant the networks have arisen to
challenge them
with the zapatista movement in in the
1990s with campaigns to ban
land mines and nuclear testing and all
sorts of
of other networked activities and so we
see a world now
the world of empires and nations faded
away now it's a world
of nations and networks and it saddens
us to see how much conflict there is
between nations and
and uh networks but that goes to uh
a point that you know we feel is is very
important to make
which is that this information
revolution can be used for good
or ill for light or for dark and
that is something very much a matter in
contention
uh right now peter and i want to double
click on the
the dark side in a moment uh but to come
to terms further
could you explain the difference for
people who don't know the difference uh
between hard power
versus soft power and then maybe like
sharp power and deal power as you guys
pointed this one
and how that relates to uh no apology
sure hard power is very traditional
uh railpolitik it's about
the size of your economy the amount of
traditionally the amount of steel
production your country had because that
would
uh let you know how much you could make
in terms of weaponry the
advance of your technology uh again for
uh usually for weapons making power
generally measured
in in that way economic military
to some extent people begin to pay
attention to the notion of informational
power through uh diplomacy
reputation matters by the way if you
watch the
pew polling on the views of the united
states in the world you know the last
few years
uh the views of the united states have
gone down very
sharply and and that's even pre-coveted
and uh so it's it's troubling to see
that development
soft power is this notion of uh
influence of how information affects the
way
people uh act believe and
uh the whole idea there is that we
challenge a little bit is
it's the notion of soft power seems to
be
seen as very favorable if you can use
soft power oh boy that's way better than
hard power
what we've pointed out is there is a
reverse of the coin
in in soft power it can be used for very
very dark purposes such as
really intervening in democratic
electoral processes as the united states
saw in 2016
but frankly as many liberal societies
have seen in recent years with uh
interventions in their systems using
propaganda and other tools to
try to muddy up the public discourse and
so that's soft power too
and and so nuopolitique in in
our idea of it is really about
trying to separate out that darker
purpose
and moving toward this uh more common uh
sense
of rights ethics the
appropriate forms of interaction and
again we see
signs of this trying to poke its head up
above the surface in things like the
united nations declaration of universal
human rights and against uh genocide
we see it in the helsinki accord on
human rights that was reached with the
soviet union back in 1975.
so there there are these elements that
are that are trying
to uh come along but they're still
drowned out very much by
by hard power uh smart power
that's not our term of course uh it's i
think associated more with professor nia
at harvard
and that's really about the the skillful
blending
of uh soft and and hard power to gain
some form of uh of advantage uh we did
come up with this notion of deal power
uh because the current american
president seems to be
quite fixated on the notion of
international relations as fundamentally
being transactional in nature
and that you can get what you want by uh
sharp
sharp dealing and uh and that's part of
this notion of sharp power
as as well it implies a certain kind of
uh cleverness in in one's uh blending of
hard soft power deal power
uh etc and i think china is to some
extent associated with notions of uh
sharp uh power so there's all this
typology
and we're not really interested in in
going down that rabbit hole we think the
distinction between heart and soft power
is fairly clear
what's not clear is that people need to
recognize that
soft power ideational power can be used
for very very dark purposes
and one of the ideas behind our
neuropolitique
is to take an ethical stand in
statecraft
and we take heart looking at things like
hans morgenthaus
politics among nations uh to see that he
too
near the end of and he's sort of
considered the you know the father of
modern father of
20th century power politics here's a guy
saying unless there are kind of rules of
the game there
are ethical limits beyond which nations
will not go
uh the system simply won't work and so
for morgenthau there's this recognition
of the need for an ethical foundation
even to power politics what we're saying
is that
this isn't simply a foundation piece
this actually should be much more of the
of the space of international
interaction should be uh bound uh onto
this
element and that in fact the hard power
the need for it
will be uh diminishing over time and
there will be diminishing returns
from the use of hard power certainly as
the united states has seen over the last
20 years
at a cost of about somewhere between
five and seven trillion dollars tens of
thousand lives
lost or shattered and of course hundreds
of thousands
and of lives lost and millions shattered
by american interventions
using uh hard power over the past few
decades so we
we think we're on to something uh better
and that's why we have uh come back
to this subject why a shorter version of
this monograph
or perspective i guess is what rand is
calling it now yes definitely our
perspective
a shorter version of this made the
handbook for public diplomacy
rutledge's new edition of that and we
were very happy to see it widely read on
the social science
research network peter i'm looking at a
wonderful
pictograph here i i don't know whose it
is but uh
thanks i really like it kind of has a
yin and yang with some pictographs in it
is that from heron uh i think so
yeah very nice um so a few more
questions and we'll give it to
the chat box uh the dark
aspect of the soft power and all this
the active measures that russia is doing
the internet research
agency the internet patrol farms or the
chinese
discourse power could you speak a little
bit about how
foreign governments are using this for
dark means
well clearly we have a situation where
all the american intelligence agencies
and and many others around the world
believe that the russians are using deep
fakes
and social media to muddy up the
political discourse in the united states
the reports i've seen are pretty
conclusive about 2016.
what people don't generally hear about
is how often these techniques are being
used
in many other countries trying to hold
uh
elections from france to cote d'ivoire
to
other other places and so this is
becoming
pretty much a norm it is you know it
a typical use of propaganda
style use but it's incredibly enabled by
advanced technology and
uh connectivity but let me just say the
united
states is not above doing this either at
the
height of our intervention in iraq
in the late aughts we paid
millions of dollars to a group to create
phony
articles to put in a newspaper uh
several newspapers
and other media owned by the us
government in iraq to try to portray an
image of the country that simply
wasn't true and stories that were were
uh deeply faked if not deep fakes
so we have to recognize
that uh they're the the guilt for
embracing the dark side of soft power uh
is wide
widespread and it's again our hope that
the rise of neural politique will create
a less permissive environment for this
by the establishment of sets of common
values and and here one of our central
ideas
is this notion of finding the issue
areas
on which there can be general agreement
and of course the
anti-genocide convention 1948
declarations of human rights
but we also see things like the global
commons
the environment would be of course a big
part of this something on which people
can
come to agreement about uh protecting
other areas of the commons would be
space
right now there's an arms race emerging
in space in direct violation
of the outer space treaty of 1967 so
this would be another
area where i think the global commons
and our attention to it
uh through a new political perspective
would be uh very very
uh helpful and there are many other uh
areas
and i want to just say before we go to
chat that david and i
have as much as we're
you might say we have a kind of mystical
view
of the potential for a new kind of
statecraft to emerge much as they are
and varnodsky and leroy had a century
ago
we're also pretty flinty-eyed about how
to get there
and so another concept in our study that
we
developed here and have been working on
for a very long time
is this idea of guarded openness it's a
deliberately ambivalent
sort of formulation that suggests we
want to foster as much openness as we
possibly can
but we want to remain as guarded as we
can also be
against the sorts of things like deep
fakes and electioneering
uh from the outside uh in our
liberal democratic processes and you can
think about it on a spectrum right where
where's the people's republic of china
today
incredibly guarded with some openness
that's allowed them to enjoy some
economic prosperity
but basically they've tended to control
social uh
unrest the united states has defaulted
uh a lot more toward openness and i
frankly i don't think we're guarded in
the right ways we're regarding the
against the wrong sorts of of of things
uh and then the european union probably
a nice blend of guardedness
and openness the global data protection
regime they
established there i think is an
excellent example
of both fostering openness while at the
same time remaining
uh substantially uh guarded so hold on
to that thought the global
commons guarded openness uh for us
at a policy level you know we're defense
analysts
and another thing that we thought was
very very important
was that nations especially in a world
where networks are rising
in importance and we are forming
alliances very often with
non-state networked actors ngos and etc
it's important for a nation to know its
own information posture
we know and all the people we work with
know exactly our military posture you
know how many missiles we have
how many ballistic submarine ballistic
missile submarines are at sea at any
given moment
all those sorts and we know that we're
spending two billion dollars a day on on
the military
what do we know about our information
posture
what is the not only the conduits that
we have the voice of america and other
things
but what's the content we're putting out
there and is it consistent with our
actions an information posture needs to
ask and ask answer questions of of that
sort
so uh i i know you probably want to go
to chat so i'll pass this back to you
peter
and my last question was going to be
about the spiritual side what de
chardin's a mega point but peter jones
has uh has that embedded in his question
so i will tag
peter in if you can ask your question
go ahead peter oh okay thanks um
i was uh curious about perhaps a
spectrum
of the noah's sphere from um
from a concept of gl of arri
creating a global consciousness which
might trend towards technology
technological view
that is the internet eventually merging
into something like
maybe not a singularity it's one idea
but
but a but a global consciousness and
inter-awareness that exceeds
nation-states but on the other end of
the spectrum
the the original chardon construct
was was a really mystical idea and there
might be a spectrum
of you know of his um
his idea was really that there would be
an evolution
in human spirit that would that had a
telos that had a directionality towards
towards uh you know a unity of human
spirit
these might not actually come together
in the same way
and and actually are you know the
the power games between nation states
hard and soft may be part of the
conflict that actually keeps us from
um from from achieving um the latter
you know it's a spiritual orientation to
that unity
you know i think it's a point
exceptionally well taken and taylard i
think had it right
you know that that is our telos that'll
make a point where
we do have this global consciousness he
didn't know about the net in the world
wide web but he knew that one day
all would be connected and and i think
if you look at wired and
and other organs of communications in in
the information age you see they have
very much a new spheric
perspective i we know kevin kelly uh
for a long time and and who is sort of
one of the founding spirits at
wired he very much is uh of this of this
mind as
as well and we think that especially
when when you consider and this is one
of the reasons we emphasize notions of
the
cooperating on the global commons we're
at a point where the future of the
planet is at
at stake and humanity needs to rise
above itself
or you know david and i spent most of
our lives thinking about issues of war
and peace and security and i
i have to say the system that we have
doesn't work very well there's too much
war it's too destructive
and the idea of going to war over
differing god
concepts or economic systems
seems increasingly absurd and i think we
now have the technology that will allow
for a discourse
that makes clear the bankruptcy
of these older concepts and it's one of
the reasons that
for for all the different ideas that
we've contributed to the defense world
this view of neopolitique something that
will be a real operating doctrine for
the newest fear
i think is more important than any other
work that we've done
thank you i might add the other the
other kind of proposal i had in the chat
was that this if that was a spectrum
another spectrum that
might conflict with it but also a line
would be the
would would be a political spectrum and
it wouldn't be left right to me it would
be the
the the different gradations of from
local to global
including a nationalism which is a type
of somewhere in the middle
and it isn't always bad you know john
ralston saul's
um had promoted a kind of positive view
of nationalism which we actually see in
canada
which is uh which is a movement away
from globalization
but is not necessarily away from you
know um
global participation global
consciousness
and so i'm starting to imagine from your
concept that
that we could start to reposition um
the different you know and not to have a
manichaean view
of of national nationalism versus
globalism which has been
which are both pretty much hard-edged uh
real politic approaches i i think that's
a very wise point
the nation state is not going gentle
into that good night
and so it has to be brought into this
process
and i think you're absolutely right
about countries like canada like sweden
and and some others uh that really are
understanding that there is the
possibility of a harmonious evolution of
nations and
and networks and uh that of course is
counterpoise to those who would use the
new technology to reassert forms of
sovereignty
so for example the social credit system
in china is an extremely
nationalist view where now you're
you know you can get a negative score on
your social credit in china if a camera
picks you up jaywalking on a street
in uh wuhan uh and and so it's
almost or orwellian and it's now as of
this year it's
mandatory for uh everybody and so
i i see uh alex warren has asked a
question about his authoritarianism
winning
and and i'd say it may not be winning
but it's certainly having its innings
and uh you know china has uh i was just
talking about their social credit system
which
is clearly authoritarian or if we wanted
to get into definitions closer to a
totalitarian sort of
initiative but hong kong looks pretty
restive
i i think xinjiang is is a problem for
them it's really an open question as to
how long china can continue to enjoy
the economic and political benefits
of the information revolution without
suffering the social consequences
and so yeah authoritarianism uh
is uh is going to be around and and
certainly
uh in in our view i think i'm speaking
for david here
we find it far less well attuned to the
potentialities of the information
age to the new sphere to neuropolitique
and that that eventually just as nation
states triumphed
over empires i think this more
interconnected network-like view even in
the world in which nation-states persist
will much much more come to the fore uh
but i i think we're in for it even when
our colleague frank fukuyama wrote the
end of history over 30 years ago
he said which said that free markets and
democracy
going to win out over everything uh even
he said it's that's going to take
centuries
it will take uh some indeterminate uh
period
but i think the new sphere concept gives
us a way
of seeking that telos that peter was
mentioning that end that that we
uh seek that certainly will work better
and and as this global consciousness
emerges the true
bankruptcy of the old system of power
politics which has
uh given us uh perpetual wars
a perpetual state of war in in the world
uh that simply drains us and and again
when you look at the causes of these
conflicts
all of them are for things that really
bear so little on what the human purpose
is
in the world the way our economies are
structured or
how we how we worship these these simply
have to stop being causes
of wars and we think that this notion of
the globe girdling realm of the mind
uh will get us to an omega point uh
one day where people will see the
bankruptcy of the old system
i'm ready for another question peter
sg you had a few questions if you can
unmute yourself and ask them
um hey john and uh and david so i'm i'm
completely new to
the work that's my first introduction to
it but the whole topic fascinates me so
i just
spammed a bunch of questions in the chat
and maybe i'll just try to ask which
ones are
are the most interesting um my
uh exploration of topics of alternatives
to hierarchical
sort of power systems has led me towards
the concept of
anarchy as a political philosophy and
i'm wondering if you guys can just chat
a bit about that and how you've seen it
apply
yeah we have used that term and uh our
use of it
is if i can put it very briefly is as of
systems that operate
and pursue a common goal without central
control
and so we have spent a lot of time
thinking about networks
and what makes for a healthy network and
at the very
top of that list of things that matter
for
for networks is their narrative what are
they about if you want to have this
pursuit of a common goal without
necessarily a central control you must
have a story
and that's part of our monograph here
about it's whose story wins which story
will
uh really predominate uh over you know a
competing story as
a story about you know the world that
doesn't change and in which traditional
power
is still the cinequanon of statecraft
uh or is it a story about being able to
seek something broader something
brighter that
can perhaps save the planet from
environmental catastrophe
or keep us from having decades worth
of space garbage circling and ruining
orbital planes
uh because we've taken war into space uh
we we think that narrative notion is
incredibly
uh important there needs to be
a social sense that emerges in these
networks that
certainly the nation has been a focus of
loyalty for
centuries now what if the focus of
loyalty is now
a social one to those like-minded in
pursuit of something like you know an
anti-land mine campaign or
an anti-war campaign more more generally
or an environmental
uh group identities can you can have a
number of identities i haven't stopped
being a bombs and bullets guy
even though i'm hoping to seek that
telos as well and i care deeply about
environmental
and other related uh issues so i i think
this notion of anarchy is
can also look inward as well because
many of us
uh have quite a few different dimensions
to
to ourselves the other elements that
make networks stronger weak have to do
with their topologies
and we feel that the greater the
interconnectivity of all with all the
greater the potential strength i think
professor metcalf metcalf's law makes
this point very well when he says the
power of a network is the square of the
number of interconnected nodes
and and i think that very well explains
how quickly the color revolution spun up
and
had so much effect uh why the arab
spring burst
on the scene though the way it did and
certainly it explains things like the
social revolutions of 1848 as well they
didn't have an internet but they had
telegraph and
there was a lot of coordinating among
european cities on on the basis of that
uh connectivity so topology of the
network matters a a great deal
as far as the technology is concerned i
think the kind of connectivity we have
today
really primes us for making this leap
to the next stage in human intellectual
evolution
and hopefully social evolution as well i
know david
has wonderful works on this and we can
make sure you have links to his studies
of how we
humans have evolved from tribes to
institutions to markets
to uh networked societies and and and i
think it's
an exceptionally profound uh work that
um i i think you'd enjoy very much it'll
give you a good sense of how to think
about
uh this this movement into a networked
age
i have a bit of a follow-up if peter
phil allow me
um when i think about you know anyone
can create a narrative
now and anyone can sort of accumulate
uh brain power towards a cause a
compelling story
i see it as a very asymmetric warfare
type of
uh power where the individual can
compete with
with more traditional states um
it leads me to wonder from uh from a
moral perspective
is asymmetric warfare in and of itself a
desirable thing
um so yeah if you could
share some thoughts on that yeah well
personally i think all warfare strives
to be asymmetric you don't want simply
to go straight at the opponent all all
good
strategy remember what sun tzu said when
your opponent is strong
in the east strike in the west do
something break the symmetry
of the situation and now as you so
rightly
pointed out we're seeing tremendous
asymmetries
uh in terms of the barriers to entry for
having influence have dropped
substantially thanks to this technology
and to my mind it's a wonderful thing
and you know this isn't simply a story
about the conduits everyone has the
conduit
but who has the content that catches on
right just about every person in the
world has a has a website
but how many of them get many clicks
right there's a
handful that dominate the the discourse
a relative handful that dominate the
discourse space
so the content that narrative who's got
the right story
and and what david and i have been uh
trying to point out is
the terrible shortcomings of the
traditional story about force and
statecraft and what is needed
and the great great potential of
uh the system that that we're talking
about here which is much more driven by
norms and
and values and common purpose
and you know in most of human history
uh power was hoarded uh
the world we're looking at is one in
which information and power
are are shared something else i would
just say and we've been
writing about this for almost 30 years
as as well
is we move into an age when what people
consider
solid hard power is actually softening
itself it's becoming less influential
and the context the narrative
the informational dimension has been
hardening and having greater
uh influence and i think that's a trend
that will continue
as as well
next all right uh rain you're up next
hey john thanks for being here and
thanks for your seminal contributions
um i want to ask your thoughts basically
on
the game b post rivalry infinite game
space and um just your thoughts but to
contextualize it
um i um i've
listened to a lot of daniel
schmuckenberger's work and
there are certain thinkers like daniel
that have
um sort of taken a big step back and
and seen that have the have the
hypothesis that
all forms of competitive game theory
combined with the exponential growth of
technology and the weaponization of
technology
is sort of a formula for for disaster no
matter what
so um maybe this is a a stretch to ask
uh someone who's kind of an expert as
yourself in
in statecraft but do you think there's a
place for post-rivalry do you think it's
possible do you think
it's um necessary
or and if you believe there's some kind
of hybrid relationship between
uh rivalrous uh local rival liberal
situation with global cooperative
situations
um i'd be curious to hear about that
yeah i
i love this question and i don't know if
any of my graduate students are
still here participating but we uh
that we go year round i'm at a military
school and one of the things i've had
them reading this quarter
is uh robert axelrod's evolution of
cooperation
and what i love about is he takes a game
theory construct the prisoner's dilemma
where you know right two prisoners in
different rooms and
everyone who's seen law and order knows
that you separate them and you say
whoever
squeals first gets the better deal and
so in game theoretic terms it always
the dominant strategy is always to rat
on the other
guy what axelrod did is he said what if
prisoner's dilemma wasn't single play
but it went out for some indefinite
period could ever could cooperation
evolve under that circumstance even in
this
dire situation and and he ran a couple
of uh computer tournaments uh
on this and uh each time
the nice program that never ratted on
the other guy first
did the best and did that in two expert
tournament tournaments
and then he played an early version of
what we would today call the infinite
game
which was evolutionary in nature that
went out
twenty thousand thirty thousand
iterations of of the game
and pointed out how even a small cluster
of cooperative regimes will gain more
and more space over time
against the more conflictually oriented
programs
and it is most most fascinating when did
he write that like 35 36 years ago
but i think bob axelrod was was on to
something as long as the window of the
future
remains indefinite i i think there is
and
and the telos is not something we're
going to try to reach in 10 years
but if we think in terms of a longer
timeline uh
my my bet is on new politique as having
a much longer life span than rail
politik
great question uh kyle you're up next
cheers thanks for a lovely talk so far
um
i've been thinking a lot about identity
inside of novopolitik
and you already alluded to it a bit
earlier and i guess
as i think as i observe networks and to
kind of allude to peter's work we've
seen
the effects of networks on this
enhancing of mimetic and tribal identity
right and as well as people being able
to find each other
uh amplify voices etc so
how does identity work in that alluding
to
what you said earlier about kind of the
decline of nationalism and
and i'm thinking of john john rob's work
here where
he also has kind of alluded to this
declining nationalism and declining
these sorts of things
so what is the role of identity inside
these politics
and how does it manifest itself
does it become even more do we become
have to go through a period of even
stronger identity politics
before we integrate and and move past
that
or is it just uh you know how do you see
that playing out
i i try to grapple with it by accepting
the idea that
i'm multi-dimensional you know i can be
an environmentalist
and a defense guy who's you know
given an oath to my country i can still
have
my country as a focus of loyalty but be
interested in
these other things as well and i i think
in particular as as we look at these
broader
narratives of of the networks they
create what benedict anderson called
the imagined community and i'm really
excited about that
because nation building is a very
fraught business
right it's uh especially in those cases
where the united states has over the
past few decades
tried to reroute the currents of culture
and history with armed force
to do nation building and it seems to me
that it is far more productive to
understand the imagined community
who do the afghans think think they are
i mean they always had
an identity it was very light at the
national level
but they were they were the people of of
the mountains
they they were the people who were the
most independent
in in the world uh they um
and there weren't xenophobes there were
always an entrepreneur
and a crossroads of trade they're a
genetic mix of many different peoples
uh they're among the most uh
multi-dimensional creatures
in the world i know that probably goes
against a lot of what people have heard
about afghanistan
these past few decades but there are
most most remarkable people
and we have to embrace the imagined
community there rather than try to do
what what we have
done so my hope is that we will see
nations and networks coexisting
in a way that will eventually tend more
to favor
this idea of that the aspects of one's
identity that look more broadly
uh nationalism has not gone away and in
the face
of this emerging networked world
the reaction of some has been to try to
double down on nationalism certainly the
notion of america first is an attempt to
to do that we're we're not out here for
the global benefit but
guess what if we don't have that global
view
even what we have at home isn't going to
last the planet is going to go to pieces
environmentally
and there are so many even issues like
transnational crime and terror will
never be dealt with all the things that
matter
require more to be dealt with than
single nations even very powerful
nations can
can deal with so i i like the idea of
identity
as as having different facets at one
point
david and i used the roman god janus to
uh depict the the spirit of of networks
if you'll remember
janus is the two-faced god the older one
looking back
the younger one looking forward and and
i think
maybe maybe janus is the right
identity for this time arthur kessler
wrote a wonderful book about this simply
entitled janus
in which he said that there is this dual
nature
that seeks to connect but at the same
time
realizes the importance of assertion of
the self and
he thought that you know social
evolution was going to play out with
this janus-like phenomenon
in in play so that's a great question
about identity no thank you
cool albert kim you're up next
okay awesome um so i'm going to
work my way up here um
thank you so much very appropriate right
i'm trying to be like you
um so my question was uh could it be the
lack of a coherent
information posture by the us uh is due
to its widespread domestic
and international destability
stabilization efforts
i found it very uh uh curious i was
reading through your white paper
and it i mean like there was this i
thought maybe you're just buttering the
defense
uh uh the defense department up but like
you know like
they don't think that yeah because i
mean like the uh the us has been pumping
out this info misinfo
uh you know uh interfering in domestic
uh
domestic and international affairs for a
long time so could it actually be that
is the
a lack of our of a coherent information
posture is because
we have our tentacles all over the place
and th this
if this is true i mean this would
support your stance that the nation
state
is not the right level at which no
politic uh can be
affected so i was wondering like what
new forms of uh
non-state organizations you see arising
like the best implement
no no no politique and also as an extra
um could you maybe speak on how the the
discrete realms the geosphere biosphere
knows here can be integrated
because i believe like the way out for
humanity is like to build this technium
to build this whole house to build the
no sphere and then integrate everything
into a single system
um so i was wondering maybe if you would
speak on that
absolutely uh wow i hope we have about
two more hours
here look i i think you're absolutely
right about
the problems with the american
information posture
the biggest problem is that our actions
have not been consistent with our
declaratory policies
and and i think this has hurt us
tremendously and again when you look at
the
the pew center's views on what's
happened to favorability ratings of the
united states in
recent years this uh bears out the uh
uh the point the military interventions
the intervention and you know frankly we
have
uh pushed for one side or another to win
in elections in different places as
as well maybe not using deep fakes like
the russians do
but it is very hard for us to be the
progenitor
of uh the newest fear and of
neopolitique when we ourselves are
betraying so many of its core values i
need to put a commercial in here at the
moment since i'm a government
employee and say that the views
expressed are mine alone that do not
reflect official government policy
uh let me move on to your points about
integrating geosphere biosphere new
neurosphere
i think this is a central challenge of
our time look if
the newest fear does not spread and
thrive
we are not going to deal with the most
urgent threat
to the biosphere uh life itself and you
know we're going to end up a barren rock
like mars
right we we know that sometime in the
past mars had
rivers that ran and a better atmosphere
and some people
say it even had a better magnetic field
back back then
so all these things are tied together
there is and
and i don't want to sound like a 19th
century transcendentalist here
but in fact one of the pieces we wrote
though years ago was entitled
transcendental destination
so you can google that but we we see all
these things as connected with each
other
and i don't see the competitive system
of nation states as one that's going to
allow that integration to occur and in
fact will create
a degradation and i don't know how if
there are any political scientists in
our zoom group today but what is the
basic assumption of power politics that
the international system is anarchic
wow that's that's a recipe for absolute
disaster particularly in the kind of
technological
age in which we live after a couple of
centuries worth
of the detritus of industrialization so
we're in
very very big uh trouble here and the
social and political structures
by which we live are inimical to the
interests of ourselves
for life on the planet and really to the
to the geosphere it
itself and i i can't uh emphasize enough
that i think the red light is absolutely
flashing but thank you for your
wonderful
and wide-ranging thoughts and that
beautiful background there i
envy it awesome thank you mr john
cool so we have time for maybe uh one or
two more questions
uh dan feldman
you're up next
okay my dad hello
hello john thank you very much for uh
coming to the store today
um my question i i'm just gonna run this
off the top of my head my question was
and i think you just
answered it because you were kind of
talking about this
transcendental alignment excuse me
alignment in this
non-competitive world i was basically
going to ask
whether i'm not sure how familiar you
are with the works of michelle
bowens and others in the common-centric
p2p
uh cosmo local uh world and david's more
familiar with them but he's
uh tutored me a little bit okay well i
guess mike my question is
um uh look
does the noah sphere require as a
prerequisite
the development of this
commons from the local level to the
cosmological level
in order to operate that essentially the
com
right now we have a bipolar world of the
of the market in the state
and essentially we need to rein
introduce
our ancient commons back into uh the
system
even with some indigenous um
mindset let's say to kind of to achieve
i believe what you've been communicating
in most of your responses and your
introduction
yeah i i'm wondering if that's if i've
got that you're absolutely right about
that
and the real question is
does the newest fear have a chance to
really get traction
and to become the you know the principal
means of our
thinking about the world and will
neuropolitique become
in the way in which society functions
going
going forward and rather than think in
terms of
requiring you know prerequisite
conditions
i i tend to think of uh you know it's
it's like the universe it all started
out dark
and then there are points of light and
where those were those points of light
and
our job is to expand and connect them up
and to cluster them
and i think the notion of the new sphere
helps that kind of clustering
along we're talking in cosmological
terms i hope i can use this
metaphor about the universe but i i
think the point is that
the overall environment is probably
hostile to the development
uh the full development of the noise
fear and neuropolitique
and that it is our job to build and gain
traction where we can and eventually we
will reach an inflection point
at which this level of consciousness
this realm of the mind that tayard and
leroy and bernotsky talked about were
going to have
uh this winning uh combination
and and would indeed take us uh beyond
now
vernon thought this would require a
cataclysm first
and and i used to think maybe he wasn't
quite right about that
but the closer we get to environmental
catastrophe the closer
we get to i think the bulletin of the
atomic scientists has the
nuclear hand closer to midnight than
it's ever been before
i hate to think that it's going to take
cataclysm to get us to that inflection
point and it is my
and i i think david's belief as well
that we see some signs of progress
uh we see a yearning among peoples among
many people's
uh for movement in this direction and so
i say let's continue to create points of
light
in the firmament and make sure that
the universe isn't made up 98 of dark
matter as at least not the
social universe uh that's that's the
hope
and uh that said
that's my belief i don't know that it's
the right answer and
and if i'm wrong about this uh
then vernodsky will be right and there
will be cataclysm that those i think are
the stakes we face today
thank you seems like a
good place to leave off um not exactly
mr sunshine
john do you have any uh final comments
uh for us today
well first of all i want to thank
everyone at the at the stoa for
making this event possible i want to
thank
my colleague david who i do not think
enough for
30 years plus of uh
certainly expanding the the brain of an
old bombs and bullets guy
into something and someone very very
different
and i want especially to thank those
who've raised questions today
that suggest to me and i hope to david
as well that
there is a sense among thoughtful people
that we need a major shift in direction
and and i hope that
the ideas that we've put forward will uh
be held in your minds as a viable option
to a system that today
a system of force and statecraft that
clearly is not working and clearly is
leading uh
toward global disaster and and so with
with that in mind i
i urge us all to you know keep
clustering
keep making more light in uh in a
universe of
of dark matter uh
we are and ideas are i think the last
best hope
tayard was very much an optimist and i'm
a great admirer
of his and when i reflect on it
even you know the hardest of hard power
advocates like hans morgenthau
said ideas values norms ethics
there is something else without which
no system of power politics or any kind
of politics will ultimately work
and so even if the wise people who
employ and practice the business of real
politic realize this then i think
there's hope for all
so uh again thank you all this has been
uh really a wonderful
hour together and uh and appreciate what
you do and
and uh the fact that you are uh
creating a virtual stoa would that we
had
more of these in the virtual world the
physical world
and that i'm a big fan of of stoicism
particularly as it emerged in
in rome and uh
which is an ironic thing for a great
empire to have some of
the most thoughtful stoics who came came
along
we teach those stoicism we have a course
on that for our students i just want you
to know here military officers
it is one of the most popular courses on
our campus
oh wow cool i salute you all thank you
again
thank you so much john uh and and david
uh take you in for for some comments as
well
just quickly sorry about my voice
i put some comments in the chat
stream about where to locate
the writings that john referred to
that just quickly uh
michael bazar's work does
overlap with ours but he's more taken
with the concept of the infosphere
dial ferguson's work which is about
two ports hierarchies then that works
by work it is about four forms
tribes institutions markets
networks and if we do draw
on the writings we got both costumes
i forget her first name eleanor
dad we shall balance particularly
in the chapter gone now the global
communist
commons but anyway john good work jerry
thank you good to see you dad good to
see you
thank you peter i really appreciate
your article about pneumatic tribes
thank you for that
thank you thank you um i'll make
announcement a morning
in a moment uh but again gentlemen thank
you so much would love to have you come
back for the stall for another
collaboration
um and uh uh upcoming events uh john
robb has
um the military analyst john rob he has
a sense maker residence series here at
the stoa
he was uh greatly influenced by david's
tribes institutions
networks theory and talks about that
often in his session so if you want to
check that out you can go at
10 a.m eastern time here at the stoa and
uh
tomorrow we have uh benito roy nora
bateson and ray back having a three-way
emergent conversation
at uh 12 30 p.m eastern time on praxis
to collective wisdom presence warmed out
at insight
it's gonna be very very awesome it's
gonna be a full house so you can rsvp to
that
on the website and
if you like these conversations that
we're having at the stoa
there's digital stoa that's emerging you
can support us here
uh on our patreon all our events are for
free and uh
we'd like to continue to have offer all
this during this difficult
time we are all facing that being said
again
thank you david and john and thank you
everyone for coming out today